如果彼得在耶路撒冷
If Peter is in Jerusalem,
我会找到他的
I will find him.
他知道我是谁
He knows who I am.
我已经不是那个你们理应憎恨的人了
I'm not the same man you once had reason to hate.
你看见了谁?
Who did you see?
我看见耶稣基督 神的儿子
I saw Jesus Christ, the son of God.
教我如何杀人
Show me how to kill.
收回那些话 卡里古拉
Take back those words, Caligula
不然我就割了你的喉咙
before I open your throat.
来啊
Do it.
你在期待罗马的新职位吗?
Were you looking forward to your new position in Rome?
跪下!! 跪拜你的新大帝!
Kneel!! In the presence of your new emperor!!
扫罗已经成了耶稣的信徒了
Saul has become a follower of Jesus.
你不能在犹太会堂传耶稣的道
You can't preach the word of jesus inside the Synagogue.
我们恰恰必须这样做
That is exactly what we have to do.
他会把我们都害死的!
He's gonna get us all killed!
本片涉及圣经内容的名词 段落 均参照和合本翻译
公元: 圣经续 第一季第9集
大马士革
--==圣城家园SCG字幕组 http://hdscg.com/==--
大数人扫罗!
Saul of Tarsus!
仅供翻译交流使用, 禁止用于商业用途
我们知道你躲着呢!
We know you're hiding!
协调: 影子
亵渎神灵者!
Blasphemer!
翻译: 飘飘行天下 波特妹子 喵喵
扫罗!
Saul!
校对: 飘飘行天下 影子
大数人扫罗!
Saul of Tarsus!
找到那个渎神者!
Find the blasphemer!
每个城门都有人带着武器把守
There are men at every gate, everybody's armed,
他们在叫你的名字
and they're screaming your name.
巴拿马 那太不可思议了
Barnabas, that was incredible.
就因为你 犹太会堂里都骚乱了
You turned the Synagogue into a riot.
世人都需要听到基督的福音
Everybody needs to hear the gospel of Christ.
无一例外
Everybody.
走这里
This way.
我能通过城门守卫 可扫罗你不行
I can get past the guards on the gate, Saul, but you can't.
关闭城门!
Shut the city gates!
出来吧
Come on.
肯定很激动人心吧 对吧?
This is gonna be exciting, eh?
什么?
What?
回到耶路撒冷去见彼得
Going back to Jerusalem, seeing Peter.
我相信他们也等不及了
I'm sure they can hardly wait.
走吧
Come on.
耶路撒冷
这说不通 怎么可能是扫罗
This doesn't make sense. Saul of all people.
他突然就疯了
He just went mad.
前一刻他还正常 而下一刻...
One moment he was normal, and then the next...
这可不是发疯 这是背叛
This isn't madness. This is betrayal.
- 他是真心实意的吗?  - 这有什么要紧?
- Did he seem genuine?  - What does it matter?
他侮辱了你
He's insulted you.
他的信念看上去非常坚定 是的
His conviction seemed sincere, yes.
找到他
Find him,
羞辱他
shame him,
然后杀了他
and kill him.
还不跪下?
Why aren't you kneeling?
她很漂亮
She's pretty.
谁?
Sorry?
你的妻子
Your wife.
谢谢夸奖
Thank you.
你对你的大帝忠诚吗?
Are you loyal to your Emperor?
当然
Of course.
有多忠诚?
How loyal?
我的丈夫和我...
My husband and I...
没问他
Not him.
我不在乎他 我问的是你
I don't care about him. I'm asking you.
你怎么表现你的忠贞?
How would you show your devotion to me?
我...
I...
奥勒留!
Aurelius!
臣在 大帝 有何事?
Yes, dear Emperor?
她不喜欢我
She doesn't like me.
我的妻子和我忠贞...
My wife and I devo...
不 她不喜欢我
No. She doesn't.
显而易见
It's obvious.
你喜欢我吗?
You like me?
我敬仰您
I worship you.
敬仰
Worship.
我喜欢这个词
I like that.
哪怕我听说你在背后议论我?
Even though you were heard talking about me?
不
No.
你怎么说的?
What were the words?
我相信他说您是疯子
I believe he said you were insane.
我绝不会说...
I would never say...
奥勒留 你是深受我叔叔信任的谋士
Aurelius, you were my uncle's trusted adviser.
是的 我也绝不会说...
Yes, and I would never say...
他也谈起过我吗?
Did he talk about me, too?
你是不是和他一起嘲笑我?
Did you laugh at me together?
这些都是别有用心的谣言
These are malicious rumors.
你忠诚吗?
Are you loyal?
毫无疑问
Absolutely.
你爱我吗?
Do you love me?
爱您
I do.
跟爱我叔叔一样多吗?
As much as you loved my uncle?
当然
Of course.
但你宣誓永远效忠于他
But you swore eternal devotion to him.
牺牲性命也在所不辞
You offered up your life.
没错 我... 我也将如此对您
I did. A... and I do the same to you.
哪怕牺牲性命?
Your life?
是的
Yes.
那就亮剑吧
Then show me your sword.
你的命
Your life.
为了罗马
For Rome.
为了大帝
For my Emperor.
愿神喜悦我的行为
May the Gods smile on my actions.
我厌倦了耶路撒冷
I am bored with Jerusalem.
巡抚 我好像还记得我们之间的争论
I seem to remember an argument between us, Governor.
平身
Stand up.
不过是场误会
It was a simple misunderstanding.
此地令人不悦
This is an irritating region.
食物劣质
The food is vile,
天气炎热
it's too hot,
对罗马或对我均无爱戴之情!
and there is no love for Rome or me!
你理应改变这一切
You shall change that.
我想也许可以...
I thought perhaps...
造个雕像
a statue.
没错
Yes.
在罗马全境立起您的雕像
Statues of you across the Empire,
从高卢直到埃及
from Gaul to Egypt.
好
Yes.
在这房间里我们就该立一座
We shall have one in this very room.
当然
We will.
我还在想神殿里也该立一座
I also thought we will have one in the temple.
代表我供万人瞻仰
My likeness in the temple for all to see.
以此作为开始
That will be a start.
好
Yes.
我们走吧
Let's go.
多美啊 是吧?
It's so beautiful, isn't it?
对 没错 请问我们能走了吗?
Yeah, it is. Can we keep moving, please?
事物之壮美竟能如此恒久 多棒啊
Amazing how something can seem so wondrous for so long,
然后...
and then...
我很想多跟你谈谈
You know, I'd love to discuss this more,
不过也许不要站在马路中央
perhaps when we're not standing in the middle of the street
人来人往都能看见
for everyone to see.
我们得去送别大帝了
We need to say our goodbyes to the Emperor.
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
为何?
For what?
为他看你的眼神
The way he looked at you.
进来
Yes.
有人请我来此
I was sent for.
对 塑造雕像的事
Yes, business with statue.
怎么了?
What of it?
他下令的时候我看见你的样子了
I saw you when he announced it.
你的表情
I saw your face.
那是因为酒坏了
The wine was off.
要是真这么做你知道后果如何
You do know what will happen if he sends it.
耶路撒冷会暴乱
Jerusalem will riot,
我的士兵会镇压成千上百的人民
and my soldiers will kill thousands.
他的雕像还会玷污了神殿
And the statue would desecrate the temple.
你倒是不在乎
Not that you'd care.
对 但你在乎
No, but you do.
我能看出来
I see that.
所以你可以阻止他
So you could stop it.
凭我?
Me?
跟他谈谈 劝阻他
Talk to him. Persuade him.
我可不这么认为
I don't think so.
但他是你的朋友
But he's your friend.
他现在是皇帝了
He's the Emperor now.
好吧
All right.
勉力一试
I'll try.
我会带他回罗马
I'll take him back to Rome,
也许等他离开这里
and maybe once he's away from here,
就会将此事抛诸脑后
he'll forget all about it.
要是连大帝最亲密的朋友也害怕
If the Emperor's closest friend is too frightened
提及此事...
to approach the subject...
会有办法的
We will find a way.
你如何能控制住一个狂人?
How do you control a madman?
这不是你一个人的问题
This is not just your problem.
这是整个犹太的问题
This is a problem for all Judea.
那又怎样?
So?
找人共同分担
So we share the burden.
彼得
So. Peter.
对 你知道我在想...
Yeah, you know, I was thinking...
也许我应该先行前去跟他们谈谈
perhaps I should go ahead and, uh, talk to them.
谈什么呢?
Well, what's to talk about?
我们现在都是信耶稣的兄弟了
We're all brothers in Christ now.
我可不确定他们也这么看
I'm not entirely sure they see it that way.
哦 你想太多了
Oh, you worry too much.
扫罗
Saul.
他来耶路撒冷了
He's here in Jerusalem.
有个神殿守卫看见他进了城
One of the temple guards spotted him entering the city.
找到他
Find him.
应该就是此处了
This must be the place.
你等在外面
Wait here.
让我先跟他们谈谈
Let me talk to them first.
然后再带你上去
And then I'll bring you up.
好的
Right.
将发生的一切如实告知他们
You tell them everything that happened
一字一句复述我的话 好吗?
just the way I told you, yes?
- 一字一句  - 好
- Word for word.  - Good.
我有点紧张
I'm a little bit nervous.
等在这
Wait here.
等着
Wait.
他已洗心革面
He's a changed man.
没人能有如此大改变
No one can change that much.
先见见他 同他谈谈
Just meet him. Talk with him.
- 不行  - 你太傻了
- No.  - You're an idiot.
你究竟明不明白你做了什么?
Don't you see what you've done?
不
No.
哦 糟了 糟了
Oh, no, no.
看来这里就是你们所有人的藏身之所了
So, this is where you're all hiding now.
你好 兄弟
Hello, brothers.
你可不是我的兄弟
You're no brother of mine.
你一个人吗?
Are you alone?
当然 我发誓我对你们没有威胁
Of course. I'm no threat, I swear.
- 西门兄弟  - 别这么叫我
- Brother Simon.  - Don't call me that.
你真的相信他已经转信耶稣了吗?
Do you really believe that he has turned to Christ?
我相信
I do.
他的信仰之火灼灼发光
His faith burns very brightly.
也许有点太旺了
Maybe a little too brightly.
我理解你为什么害怕
I understand your fears.
真的
I do.
但我已经受洗再世为人了
But I have been baptized and made new again.
- 哦 真的吗?  - 多马
- Oh, have you now?  - Oh, Thomas.
在去大马士革的路上 耶稣显身在我面前
I was on the road to Damascus when Jesus visited me.
你不配呼他的名!
You don't get to speak his name!
西门 请听他说
Simon, please.
我们正当有所成就 有所建造
We were getting somewhere, building something,
然后你追随而来 将一切摧毁殆尽
and then you came along, and you burnt it all down.
没错
Yes.
然后呢?
And?
然后我现在改信基督了
And now I turned to Christ.
他总是这样吗?
Is he always like this?
只有当他清醒的时候
Only when he's awake.
出去
Get out.
扫罗
Saul.
彼得 约翰
Peter. John.
好极了
How wonderful.
我正发愁没法让人理解我
I was having trouble making myself understood.
你已经改信基督
You've turned to Christ.
彼得 这不对 我知道
Peter, this is not right. I know it's not.
我知道这看起来像什么样子
I know how this looks.
但我... 我可以为他作保
But I... I can vouch for him.
我想和他单独谈谈 就我和你
I want to talk to him alone. Just me and you.
我和你
Me and you.
我们从你去大马士革说起
We'll start on the road to Damascus.
巴拿马不是已经和你说过...
Why hasn't Barnabas already talk...
我想听你亲口说
I want to hear it from your mouth.
彼得 我们应该开始计划...
Peter, we need to start planning...
我要你无所保留 从头讲起
You are going to tell me everything from the beginning.
但是我是你同信基督的兄弟
But I am your brother in Christ.
从头讲起
From the beginning.
就好像我一直都眼盲
It was like I'd always been blind,
而现在第一次目明了
but now I saw for the very first time.
你不相信我 对吧?
You don't believe me, do you?
- 你曾想杀死我  - 确实
- You wanted me dead.  - I did.
所以你应该理解我的谨慎
So you'll understand my caution.
对
Yes.
但这一切确实有点荒谬
But this is all a bit ridiculous, surely.
我知道自己做过什么 彼得
I know what I've done, Peter.
但在楼下听你说了这么多
But listening to you all downstairs,
好像你已经忘记
it was like you'd forgotten
耶稣教过你要宽容
that Jesus had taught you forgiveness.
我是说 你跟他同住 知道他说过的话
I mean, you lived with him. You know his message.
所以... 抱歉 但我不明白
So... so, sorry, but I'm confused.
你说得对 我确实与他同住过
You're right. I did live with him.
所以别教训我了
So don't start lecturing me.
他是什么样的?
What was he like?
他是我最好的朋友 老师
He was my best friend and my teacher
我的兄弟 我的主和主人
and my brother and my lord and master.
他曾是...
He was...
他是纯粹的爱
He is pure love.
我想念他
I miss him.
我不
I don't.
我感觉得到他... 就在这里
I feel him... in here.
他的精神在我心中燃烧
His spirit burns within me.
我们都被圣灵降临过
We've all been visited by the holy spirit.
我也感觉得到他
And I feel him, too.
我只是希望有时
I just wish sometimes
事情能稍微明了些
that things were a little clearer.
对我而言已经非常清楚了
It's all perfectly clear to me.
真的吗?
Really?
对
Yes.
我是迦玛列的学生
I am a student of Gamaliel.
我是一名法利赛学者
I am a Pharisaic scholar,
而你与我天赋不同
while you have different talents.
但在耶稣的连结下 我们可以携手创造奇迹
But together, bound by Jesus, we can work wonders.
你看不出来吗?
Don't you see?
你怎么能跟他一同生活过
How can you have lived with him,
听过他的言语 触摸过他的圣体
heard his message, touched him,
却仍不明事理呢?
and still not see?
有人在下城区看到他了
He was seen in the lower city.
本来我确定能抓到他 但还是被他逃脱了
I was sure that we would have him, but he evaded capture.
你还要被这个人愚弄几次?
How many times must this man make a fool of you?
我要搜遍全城每寸土地 直到抓到他
I will comb every inch of the city until he is caught.
我会找到他的 我发誓
I will find him. I swear.
如果大帝您完事了 那就该走了!
If the Emperor is finished, then it's time to leave!
这么快?
Already?
你在罗马可以找到质量更好的
You will find a much higher quality in Rome.
更饥渴热切的
Much more eager.
我等不及回家了
I can't wait to be home.
彼拉多那个傻瓜怎么样了?
What about that fool, Pilate?
- 他想要什么?  - 哦 没什么
- What did he want?  - Oh, nothing.
就是更加诚惶诚恐而已
Just more groveling.
快 马等着呢
Come on. Your horse is waiting.
我跟你比赛谁先到约帕
I'll race you to Joppa.
那个女孩不怎么喜欢我
That girl didn't like me very much.
祝陛下旅途一路顺风
May our Emperor have a safe and uneventful journey.
万岁 凯撒!
Hail, Caesar!
- 没事了  - 不!
- It's all right.  - No!
没事了 大比大
It's all right, Tabitha.
是我 他已经走了
It's me. He's gone.
结束了
It's over.
现在如何?
What now?
我还以为终于能安生点了
I thought we might finally have some peace.
大帝已经启程离开了
Well, our Emperor has departed.
但他给耶路撒冷留了一份大礼
But he has left a present for Jerusalem.
实际上 是专门给大祭司的大礼
In fact, it is specifically for the High Priest.
哦?
Oh?
大帝的一座雕像
A statue of his likeness.
他要求放在神殿里
Which he commands to be placed in the temple itself.
你也可以将之视作其神威和权柄的警示
As a reminder, if you wish, of his divinity and his power.
这雕像会玷污了神庙
A graven image would defile the temple
破坏我们最神圣的戒律
and break one of our most sacred commandments.
他... 不能这么做
He... he cannot do this.
但他已然如此
And yet he does.
但以理书预言过此种时刻
The Book of Daniel foretells a moment such as this,
会招致死亡和毁灭
and it promises death and destruction.
现在你有了新的神 一位罗马人
Well, now you have a new god, and he is Roman.
你手上沾满了成千上百人的血 彼拉多
Well, you have the blood of thousands on your hands, Pilate.
再多几千又何妨?
What's a few thousand more?
只要你控制好自己的人民就没事 所以
Not if you control your people, which is why
你要以客人身份跟我留在这里...
you will stay with me here as a guest...
提醒他们希律王和他的罗马同盟
to remind them of the strong bond
之间的纽带牢不可破
between the Herod and his Roman allies.
这可不是玩玩政治手段
This is not about political maneuvering.
我们说的可是神庙的毁灭!
This is about the destruction of the temple!
你能小声点吗?
Will you keep your voice down?
我们肯定能达成共识的一点是
The one thing I'm sure we can agree upon
此事不能公之于众
is that this cannot become public knowledge.
要是狂热教徒听说了此事
If the Zealots heard about this,
明早我们脚下就要尸体成堆了
we'd be knee-deep in corpses by morning.
巡抚 我们一直都在合作
Governor, we've always worked together
谋求共同点
to find a common ground.
我把你不喜欢的人钉在十字架上 而你...
Well, I crucify your undesirables, and you...
你又做了什么?
What do you do?
你难道忘了不久前还来找我
Has it been so long since you came to me
说我们是一荣俱荣 一损俱损吗?
and told me that we stand and fall togeher?
真的需要我提醒你 我为了这个地区的和平
Do I really need to remind you of all that I've done
所做的一切吗?
to ensure peace in this region?
该亚法 这是大帝的愿望
Caiaphas, this is the emperor's wish.
这不是我的问题 是你的
It isn't my problem. It's yours.
看着办吧
Deal with it.
一定还有别的办法解决这件事
There has to be a different way to approach this.
如果我们齐心协力来维护这个地区的稳定
If we work together to keep the region stable
与安宁还有... 几乎不招惹注意
and calm and... invisible, almost,
那我想大帝
then I think the emperor
会为其他事分心
may well be distracted by other things.
那倒挺容易的
That should be easy.
我们已经至少一星期没有骚乱了
We haven't had a riot here for at least a week.
这还不够
That's not enough.
得有人牺牲
You need blood.
仅仅安宁稳定是不够的
It's not enough to be quiet and stable.
当然可能稍有裨益
Although, it might help.
你的卡里古拉喜欢鲜血的滋味
Your Caligula has a taste for blood.
所以我们找个人公开处死
So we find someone, destroy them very publicly,
并且让他知道
and let him know all about it.
那样看起来就像整个犹太团结一心
It will seem as if the whole of Judea is united
接受罗马作它的主人了
and accepts Rome as its master.
不过是演戏而已
It's a piece of theater, that's all.
那谁是替罪羊呢?
And who is this scapegoat?
你们有没有听说过大数人扫罗?
Have either of you heard of a man called Saul of Tarsus?
他是谁?
Who is he?
他曾是个好人
He was a good man.
但他被拿撒勒人腐蚀了
But he was corrupted by the Nazarenes,
如今他... 成了渎神者 是我们共同的威胁
and now he is a... a blasphemer and a danger to us all.
威胁?
A danger?
据我所知 拿撒勒人的信仰是很平和的
From what I understand, the Nazarene faith is a peaceful one.
他们宣称耶稣是王 而非你们的大帝...
They claim Jesus is king, not your emperor...
说他是弥撒亚 神 而非你的卡里古拉
that he is the Messiah, a God, not your Caligula.
这是对罗马权威赤裸裸的挑战 不是吗?
It's a direct challenge to Rome's authority, is it not?
当你想想因为无谓地处死耶稣
When you consider all the trouble caused
而引起的所有麻烦...
by the needless execution of Jesus...
不是无谓的 一点也不
Not needless. Not needless at all.
我以为我们是来讨论
I thought we were here to discuss
你口中自己深爱的城市和人民
the destruction of the city that you claim to love so well
遭受毁灭屠杀的事
and the massacre of your people.
而这就是你能想到的?
And this is all you can offer?
拜托 告诉我... 你要怎么做?
Please, tell me... what will you do?
不 亲爱的...
No, my dear...
巡抚夫人 压迫我们民族的人
wife of the governor and depressor of our nation.
问题该是 你要怎么做?
The questions is, what will you do?
你知道 在来这的路上我非常兴奋
You know, when I was coming here, I was so excited.
巴拿巴跟我说了你好多事
Barnabas had told me so much about you.
没错 我知道我们以前是什么关系
And yes, I know what we were to each other before.
但我想... 我真心地想
But I thought... I genuinely thought
当我见到你的时候 你会比任何人都...
that when I saw you, you more than anyone...
我本以为我们的会面将不可思议
I thought it would be incredible.
而你却只是坐在那儿评判我
But you just sit there and judge me.
你说他为什么选择了你?
Why do you think he chose you?
因为没有人能够阻止我抓你
Because nobody could have stopped me from getting to you
除了他
except him.
让我们出去
Let's go out.
让我们去宣扬他的福音
Let's preach his message.
现在我们可以露面了
Now we can go out.
因为你 我们东躲西藏!
Because of you, we've been hiding!
你就不能放下这事吗?！
Will you never let this go?!
你们怎么没人践行自己所宣扬的道?
Do none of you practice what you preach?
- 没那么简单!  - 没有吗?!
- It's not that easy!  - Isn't it?!
尽管你们内心都有最伟大的馈赠
You all bicker and prattle like children
却全像孩子一样斗嘴吵闹!
when inside each of you is the greatest gift!
而你们必须与人类分享那馈赠!
And you have to share that with mankind!
你一定要! 我也是!
You have to! And I have to, too!
你威胁我女儿了!
You went after my daughter!
没错
Yes, I did.
我过去一直在伤害你 彼得
All I've ever done is hurt you, Peter.
耶稣应该杀了我 但他没有
Jesus should have struck me down, but he didn't.
他原谅了我
He forgave me.
而我也必须请求你的原谅
And I must beg you for your forgiveness, too.
他难道从来无需原谅你什么吗 彼得?
Has he never had to forgive you for anything, Peter?
要知道 当亚拿尼亚来我家的时候
You know, when Ananias came to my house,
他说是耶稣派他来的
he told me that Jesus had sent him.
他告诉亚拿尼亚我会受折磨...
He told Ananias that I will suffer...
我会为他之名受折磨
that I will suffer for his name.
我绝不会原谅自己对你的所做所为
Oh, I will never forgive myself for what I did to you,
但我很害怕...
but I am scared...
我害怕现在所受的苦
I am so scared that the pain I feel right now
比起将来的苦根本不值一提
is nothing compared to what will come.
逃跑是更轻松的选择 但我不能那么做
It would be easier to run, but I can't.
现在...
Now...
我们能开始了吗?
can we begin?
我在找人
I'm looking for someone.
大数人扫罗
Saul of Tarsus.
他在老城
Old town.
我们不能走
Well, we can't go.
我们哪也不能去
We can't go anywhere.
我们是困在我父亲宫殿里的囚徒
We are prisoners in my own father's palace.
那我们留下来
So we stay.
又如何呢?
And do what?
等雕像一到 就会血流成河
When that statue arrives, there will be carnage.
我们会因为与罗马的关系
We'll be ripped to pieces
而被碎尸万段
because of our association with Rome.
所以我们必须做好准备
So we must prepare.
准备?
Prepare?
你在说什么?
What are you talking about?
罗马帝王的雕像
A statue of the Roman emperor
要放置在我父亲的神庙中
will be placed in my father's temple,
神庙将受到玷污
and it will be defiled.
对 耶路撒冷人会奋起反抗 战争一触即发
Yes, and Jerusalem will rise up, and there will be war.
没错
Exactly.
所以我们要回到加利利
So we need to be back in Galilee.
走得远远的
Far away.
不
No.
你还不明白吗?
Don't you see?
彼拉多绝不可能逃过此劫
There is no way that Pilate can survive this.
等雕像到达之日 你作为加利利的希律王
When the statue comes, you, the Herod of Galilee,
必须在这里准备好取而代之
must be here, ready to take his place,
夺回本该属于你的东西
reclaim what it rightfully yours,
除掉耶稣的信徒 永绝后患
and get rid of these Jesus followers once and for all.
谁在那儿?
Who's there?
彼得干嘛还跟扫罗说话?
Why is Peter even talking to Saul?
巴拿巴替他说好话
Barnabas has vouched for him.
但正如你所言 我们的主为什么拣选他?
But as you said, why would our Lord pick him?
感觉不对
Doesn't feel right.
我不知道
I don't know.
耶稣总是出乎我们意料 不是吗?
I mean, Jesus was always surprising us, wasn't he?
大祭司想召见大数人扫罗谈话
The high priest wishes to speak with Saul of Tarsus.
我相信他就藏在你们中间
Now, I believe that he is hiding here amongst you
就躲在这附近
in this neighborhood.
要是有人知道他在哪儿
If anyone knows where this man is,
那最好现在就告诉我
then they would do well to tell me now.
玛利亚?
Mary?
我要...
I need...
我要立刻见彼得
I need to see Peter now.
我... 我马上得走
I... I have to go now.
你能... 我本来要去送干净亚麻布的
Can you... I was supposed to deliver fresh linen.
我来帮你做 放心
I'll do that. It's fine.
怎么回事? 他们有危险吗?
What is it? Are they in danger?
是的
Yes.
不 我... 我不... 我们都有危险
No. I... I... I don't... we all are.
或许
Maybe.
我不确定
I don't know.
慢着
Oh, wait.
给你
Here.
- 为了我们的事业  - 约亚拿...
- For the cause.  - Joanna...
请收下
Please.
我也想帮忙
I want to help.
谢谢
Thank you.
我会尽快回来
I'll be back as soon as I can.
尽快...
As soon as...
那是...?
Was that...?
约亚拿 刚那女人是把钱拿走了吗?
Joanna, did I just see that woman take money?
那些钱我们不需要 我们还有很多
We don't need it, we have plenty of money.
钱是给谁?
Who is it for?
给那些信徒 帮助他们传道用
The Apostles, to help them spread the word.
传...
The word...
耶稣的道?
of Jesus?
在发生了这一切之后?
After everything's that's happened?
是的
Yes.
在你说我疯了之后
After you called me insane.
但是救了你的命
And saved your life.
这是我的信仰 苦撒
It is my faith, Chuza.
我的爱人... 我感到绝望
My love... I despair.
在遇到耶稣之前 你恬静 善良 像其他人一样
Before Jesus, you were quiet and good and like all the rest.
但是现在...
But now...
我不知该拿你如何是好
I just don't know what to do with you.
我不能再沉默下去
I cannot be silent.
你总是这么跟你丈夫说话吗?
Do you always talk to your husband like that?
当然
Of course.
谁告诉你能这么跟他说话的?
Who told you you could speak that way?
耶稣给我的力量
Jesus gave me the strength.
谁是耶稣?
Who is Jesus?
跟我说说他
Tell me about him.
我们该如何阻止他们?
How do we stop it?
我们会去的 对吧?
We are going to stop it, aren't we?
就凭我们去和罗马军队抗衡?
Us against the Roman army?
那是我们的神殿
It's our temple.
我是说我都不确定我们是否有能力 甚至有需要这么做
All I'm saying is I'm not sure if we can, even if we wanted to.
- 也许我们不该涉险  - 什么?
- Maybe we shouldn't try.  - What?
但以理书...
The Book of Daniel...
- 约翰  - 但以理书中早就预示了此种时刻
- John.  - The Book of Daniel foretells this moment.
"在神殿内 那行毁坏可憎的
"At the temple, he will set up an abomination
如飞而来"
that will cause desolation."
没错
That's right.
"必有一王
"The ruler who will come
来毁灭这城和圣所"
will destroy the city and the sanctuary."
那又如何?
So?
"至终必如洪水冲没
"The end will come like a flood.
必有争战 一直到底"
War will continue to the end."
没错 无休止的战争
Exactly. Eternal war.
耶稣在警示我们
Jesus warned us.
他认为事态会比想象中更严重
He said it'd be worse than anything ever imagined.
"直到所定的结局" 这可能就是结局
"Until the end." This could be the end.
- 你是说...  - 我不知道
- Are you saying...  - I don't know,
但是他确实是这么告诉我们的
but he did tell us.
是的 当那可憎之物立于
Yes, when the abomination stands
不属于它的地方 那么...
where it does not belong, then...
那么耶稣将会归来
Then Jesus will return.
我们找到他之后要杀鸡儆猴
When we find him, let's make a spectacle of the event.
让大家都瞧瞧
Let the world see what happens
背叛大祭司的下场
when you betray the high priest.
- 也许吧  - 也许?
- Maybe.  - Maybe?
这个男人让你蒙羞
That man is laughing at you.
没有见到他本人难下定论
Well, that's hard to know without seeing him in person.
噢 那显然你有更好的主意
Oh, so you have a better plan, clearly.
他是个学者 迦玛列的学生
He's a scholar. A student of Gamaliel's.
更重要的是 他也是犹太人
And, more importantly, a Jewish brother.
如你所说 我们是可以将其乱石砸死
We could have him stoned, as you suggest.
但是能让他回心转意不是更好
But how much better if we were to win him back
岂不也证明了神的大能?
and thereby prove the power of god?
你仅仅只想和他谈谈
You're just going to talk to him.
我要向全世界证明神殿真正的能力
I'm gonna show the world the true power of the temple.
该亚法
Caiaphas.
长久以来 我们定罪和责难他人
We've condemned and blamed
将自己的观点强加于别人头上
and bludgeoned our opinion on others for too long.
并不奏效
It isn't working.
罗马在展示实力时可从不犹豫
Rome has no such qualms about showing its strength.
"不可报仇 也不可埋怨你本国的子民
"Do not seek revenge or bear a grudge,
却要爱人如己"
but love your neighbor as yourself."
好吧 那你应该把利未记这本书献给大帝
Well, perhaps you should send the Book of Leviticus to the emperor,
反正你认为它可以解决我们一切问题
since you clearly seem to think it will solve all our problems.
我会和扫罗谈谈 然后再决定如何行事
I will talk to Saul, and then I'll decide what to do.
到那时 也就没有什么好争论的了
Till then, there's nothing more to discuss.
神殿内的雕像... 耶稣警告过我们
A statue in the temple... Jesus warned us of this.
我们得想个办法
We need a plan.
我们需要做些... 什么
We need to do... something.
抱歉在这种时刻还要让你为此事烦恼
Sorry to burden you with this on top of everything else.
扫罗怎么样?
How's Saul?
他...
He's...
让你恼火? 自负? 还是傲慢?
Irritating? Vain? Arrogant?
他煽动众人砸死司提反
He encouraged the crowd to stone Stephen.
威胁我的女儿
He came after my daughter.
带着人手穿越荒漠来杀我
He dragged men across the desert to kill me.
他说得好像自己领导一切 可他甚至都不了解耶稣
He talks like he's in charge, and he never even knew Jesus.
然而这并不要紧
But still, it shouldn't matter.
你相信他吗?
You believe him?
你要知道神殿守卫在缉拿他
You know the temple guards are hunting for him.
这就是最好的证明
That's proof in itself.
为什么你就不能接纳他呢?
Why didn't you welcome him in?
你告诉过我耶稣曾濯洗过你的双脚
You told me Jesus washed your feet once,
他是如何将万恶扭转
how he upturned the order of everything.
没有人是极弱 极穷 极恶的
No one was too weak, too poor, too sinful.
没人该被拒之门外
No one could be turned away.
哎 巴拿巴
Oh, Barnabas.
他不是那个傲慢的人 我才是
He's not the arrogant one. I am.
不
No.
为什么选他?
Why him?
开门!
Open up!
快开门!
Open the door!
开门!
Open up!
我说快开门!
Open up, I say!
我们在找大数人扫罗!
We're looking for Saul of Tarsus!
快开门!
Open the door!
开门!
Open up!
开门! 赶紧开门!
Open up! Open the door!
开门!
Open the door!
情况会有多糟?
How bad will it be?
如果我们计划周密 就可以限制伤亡人数
If we plan carefully, we can limit the loss of life.
- 限制?  - 是的
- Limit it?  - Yes.
- 限制到多少?  - 我们应该预估
- To what?  - We should assume
全境叛乱的情况
there'll be a full-scale rebellion.
那时恐怕罗马人的性命也难以保证
I fear there will be Roman lives lost, as well.
那意味着多少?
What does that mean?
几百? 还是上千?
Hundreds? Thousands?
- 我担心的是这并不是结束  - 对
- I fear that won't be the end of it.  - No.
我认为他们会多次尝试毁灭雕像
I imagine there will be several attempts to destroy the statue.
那么骚乱会持续几周 也许几个月
This will last several weeks, maybe months,
取决于他们多久才能接受现实
depending on how long it takes for them to accept it.
为什么要他们接受?
Why should they accept it?
- 克劳迪娅  - 不!
- Claudia.  - No!
我们必须阻止此事发生
We have to stop it coming.
怎么阻止?
How?
认真想想对策
We think. We plan.
你可是犹太省的巡抚
You're the governor of Judea.
这件事情无法阻止
It can't be stopped.
我们只能想想对策
We can only plan for its arrival.
我知道 我感同身受
I know. I feel the same.
但我们能做的有限
But that's all we can do.
我们必须增派守军
We must reinforce the garrison.
我没法相信你们
I can't believe you.
这可能是神殿的毁灭
This could be the end of the temple.
你们怎能只是袖手旁观并且...
How can you stand by and...
那你怎能不想耶稣回来?
How can you not want Jesus to return?
我当然想
I do. Of course I do.
但你们并不能确保
But you can't be sure of that.
答应我你们不会袖手旁观
Tell me you won't just sit by and watch it happen.
都不说话?!
Neither of you?!
西门
Simon.
好了 现在宣布个好消息
Well, now. Some good news.
我们欢迎扫罗... 成为我们信基督的兄弟
We welcome Saul... as our brother in Christ.
我有很多话要问你们
There is so much I need to ask you.
因为在楼上听完彼得的话
Because, listening to Peter upstairs,
我认为你们并没有完全
I'm worried you're not fully engaged
领会到耶稣的精髓
in Jesus' message.
你们都疯了
You've all lost your minds.
所有人
All of you.
- 这是我的错  - 不要去 扫罗
- This is my fault.  - No, Saul.
我必须要弥补
I have to make it right.
- 外面有神殿守卫 扫罗  - 我不在乎
- The temple guards, Saul.  - I don't care.
我跟过去
I'll go.
我去好一些
It's better that it's me.
西门!
Simon!
要是你能听我一言 你就知道我是对的!
If you just listen to me, you'll realize I'm right!
开门! 扫罗!
Open up! Saul!
大数人扫罗!
Saul of Tarsus!
西门!
Simon!
我就知道我会抓到你的
I knew I'd catch you.
因为你又蠢嗓门又大
You and your stupid loud mouth.
你就是不知何时应该闭嘴 是吗?
You just don't know when to shut up, do you?
再来点?
More?
我听说如果你想见某人
I've heard that if you want to meet certain people,
就该来这里
then this is the place to come.
罗马的敌人?
Enemies of Rome?
我得到重要消息
I have information,
需要告诉他们
and it is vital I get it to them.
要不然整座城市都将毁于一旦
The city will be destroyed otherwise.
战神马耳斯啊 倾听我的声音
Hear me, Mars.
请在此地停止你对战争的渴求
Please halt your lust for war in this place.
灶神维斯太啊 倾听我的声音
And hear me, Vesta.
请保佑我们家族不受到伤害
Please protect this household from harm.
抱歉 无意打扰
I'm sorry. I didn't mean to disturb.
留下来
Stay.
求你
Please.
你和我丈夫计划好了吗?
Did you plan well with my husband?
这座城市会毁灭吗?
Will the city be crushed?
我有命在身
I have my orders.
对 我忘了
Oh, I forgot.
你只是个士兵
You're just a soldier.
对
I am.
那你的人生肯定非常简单
How easy your life must be.
还有别的事吗?
Is there anything else?
没有了 退下吧
No. Go away.
等等
Wait.
我很害怕
I'm afraid.
你是如何做好准备去应对这种事的?
How do you prepare yourself for something like this?
我确信事情不会走到那步田地
I'm sure it won't come to that.
不
No.
在此之前我会被传召去罗马
I'll be called to Rome before then.
大帝一直盯着我
The emperor has fixed his eye on me,
他会用我来惩罚彼拉多
and he will use me to punish Pilate.
那你会怎么做?
What will you do then?
我会...
I would...
不会有这种事发生
I would not let that happen.
那如果是强制命令呢?
And if it were expressly ordered?
你会保护我吗?
Would you defend me?
我保证你的丈夫会为你而战
Your husband would fight for you, I'm sure.
你们男人
You men.
摧毁东西多容易
How easily you destroy things.
- 我只是...  - 我知道
- I'm just...  - I know.
我都知道
I know.
下去吧
Just go.
非常好
Yeah, very well.
带他上楼
Take him upstairs.
这是第一步
This is the first step.
你想走现在就可以走
You can get up and leave now if you want.
以后也不会再见到我
You'll never see me again,
我们不会来打扰你
and we'll let you live in peace.
我要和你们领头的谈谈
I need to talk to your leader.
神殿的未来在此一举
The future of the temple depends on it.
我知道波阿斯死了
I know Boaz is dead.
波阿斯从来都不是我们领头的
Boaz was never our leader.
第二步会带你跨过那道槛
The second step takes you across the threshold.
这之后就没法回头了 西门
There's no return after that, Simon.
你认识我?
You know me?
我们知道你属于哪派
We know what you are.
我们也接受你的信仰
And we accept your beliefs.
如果你迈出第二步
We will protect you, and you will protect us
我们将会保护你 你也会保护我们
if you take the second step.
好的
All right.
行
Yes.
那... 说吧
So... talk.
"我们日用的饮食 今日赐给我们
"Give us this day our daily bread,
免我们的债 如同我们免了人的债
and forgive us our trespasses
如同我们免了人的债
as we forgive those who trespass against us.
不叫我们遇见试探
and lead us not into temptation,
救我们脱离凶恶
but deliver us from evil.
阿门"
Amen."
我要杀一个人
I want a man be killed.
这群人中是否会有一人...
Will one of the parcels...
你把他带来给我们
I want you to bring him to us.
最终背叛?
Commit the ultimate betral?
我很抱歉
I'm so sorry.